A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726 FA739F
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726
1936-2005
1950s-1990s
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA739F
55.1 Cubic Feet Document boxes 742-886.
Other Finding Aids
For descriptions of Ford Foundation Catalogued Reports, please refer to the following finding aids (arranged by Report Number):
FA739A Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 1-3254
FA739B Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 3255-6261
FA739C Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286
FA739D Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774
FA739E Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 11775-13948
FA739G Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980
Conditions Governing Access
Catalogued Reports are open for research with select reports restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
The Catalogued Reports are arranged numerically by an arbitrary call number assigned during cataloging, from 1 to approximately 20,000.
Biographical / Historical
In the early 1970s, the Ford Foundation's archives staff began to identify and catalog individual reports, policy and programming documents, and program evaluations in an effort to create an internal lending-library of useful documents. Many of the Catalogued Reports were physically culled from the former Foundation officers' and staff's archival collections of 'office files'. When those collections of 'office files' were later processed, and finding aids created, an appendix of "Reports Removed" (or, Reports Transferred") was added to the finding aids.
By 1977 the collection included more than 3,500 reports, and by 1979 some 5,000 reports had been cataloged.
Duplicated copies of the reports were also created on microfiche, and later microfilm.
Scope and Contents
The Ford Foundation's Catalogued Reports collection includes policy and programming documents, program evaluations, and periodic program status reports produced by Foundation officers and staff, as well as consultants and grantees. Some published material produced by Ford Foundation grants is also included in the collection. The collection also includes some of the Ford Foundation's own publications, such as the Annual Reports and newsletters.
- Evaluation of the Ford Foundation's grantmaking (1994-1998) aimed at advancing the status of women in Russia (Reports 013949), 1999 (Box 742, Reel R-9299)
  Program Name
  International Affairs
  Women's rights -- Russia (Federation)
- Transition update memos and related documents (Reports 013950), 1996 (Box 742, Reel R-9299)
  Abstract/Summary
  Various interoffice memos from Susan Berresford to Ford Foundation staff concerning transition updates and program planning changes, as well as copies of New York Times and The Chronicle of Philanthropy articles addressing Susan Berresford's appointment a
  Office of the President
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Office management; Endowments -- Officials and employees; Staff meetings
- Recommendations concerning the future funding of the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research, December 8 (Reports 013951), 1997 (Box 742, Reel R-9299)
  "There has been a paradigm shift in the way CGIAR sees its role in agricultural development: from a strict focus on producing high-yield agricultural commodities to ... a concomitant set of issues, such as the environment, gender equality, and policies."
  Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS)
  Agriculture -- International cooperation; Agriculture -- Research
- National affairs project evaluations: Inventory list (Reports 013952), 1999 (Box 742, Reel R-9299)
  "This collection contains 209 evaluations of projects prepared by the Project Evaluation Unit of the Office of the Vice President, Division of National Affairs, between 1968 and 1980. Although a few of the reports evaluate Foundation initiatives or groups[…]Document consists entirely of inventory list on grants, organized by report number, title, year and month.
  Program Division/Office of the Vice President
  Related Grant Number
  06990022
  Related Grantee Name
  The Ford Foundation
  Ford Foundation Series
  Inventory list
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States; Endowments -- Program-related investments -- United States
- Education: a review of the Foundation's work in elementary, secondary and higher education, 1990. (Reports 013953) (Box 742, Reel R-9299)
  Education and Culture
  Education
- Blaming the victims: the 12 November 1991 massacre in Dili, East Timor, and the response of the Indonesian government, Feb. (Reports 013954), 1992 (Box 742, Reel R-9299)
  International Affairs;Rights and Social Justice;Developing Countries Program
  08200593
  International Commission of Jurists
  Human rights -- East Timor; Human rights -- Indonesia
- Tragedy in East Timor: report on the trials in Dili and Jakarta (Reports 013955), 1992 (Box 742, Reel R-9299)
- Farmers' experiences of land tenure and the management of local resources: a case study from North Shewa, 1974-1994 (Reports 013956) (Box 742, Reel R-9299)
  Title sufficient as abstract.
  Africa and the Middle East/Eastern & Southern Africa
  09450654
  Food and Agricultural Research Management Ltd
  Land tenure -- Ethiopia -- Shewa -- Case studies
- A reconnaissance of Simen Mountains National Park and buffer zone, 23rd March-4th April, 1994, May 1994. (Reports 013957) (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Report of visit by a team from FARM-Africa.
  Environmental protection -- Ethiopia -- Simen Mountains National Park
- Forest management system of Ethiopia: overview and options for future development (Reports 013958), 1994 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Related Conference
  Participatory Forest Management Workshop (1994: Addis Ababa, Ethiopia)
  Forest management -- Ethiopia -- Congresses
- Participatory Forest Management Workshop, March 1994. (Reports 013959) (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Unedited version of workshop proceedings.
  Forest management -- Congresses
- Participatory Forest Management Workshop: proceedings, September 1994. (Reports 013960) (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
- Coping with diversity (Reports 013961), 1993 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Discussion of race relations in the United States and the world.
  Africa and the Middle East
  09451358
  African Centre for the Constructive Resolution of Disputes Education Trust
  Race relations
- Women and development in Bangladesh: challenges and opportunities (Reports 013962), 1989 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Asia/Bangladesh
  08300792
  Women for Women
  Women in development -- Bangladesh; Women -- Bangladesh -- Economic conditions; Women -- Bangladesh -- Social conditions; Technical assistance -- Bangladesh
- Planning Meeting of International Freedom of Expression Organizations: briefing book (Reports 013963), 1992 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  09301197
  Canadian Committee to Protect Journalists
  Planning Meeting of International Freedom of Expression Organizations (1992: Montreal, Canada)
  Journalists -- Congresses; Freedom of speech -- Congresses
- Meeting of the International Freedom of Expression Exchange General Meeting: Minutes (Reports 013964), 1994 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  International Freedom of Expression Exchange General Meeting (1994: New York, NY)
- Briefing notes: International Freedom of Expression Exchange, May 13-15, New York 1994. (Reports 013965) (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Meeting schedule and agenda, appendices, IFEX clearing house subscriber questionnaire responses, and Executive director's report on the progress and activities of the IFEX clearing house, 1993-94.
- Strengthening Russia's labor policy: a perspective from the U.S. (Reports 013966), 1994 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Originally published in Russian in Chelovek i trud (Man and labor), Moscow, 1994. The development of a market economy in Russia. Report is in both English and Russian.
  09200899
  The Rand Corporation/Duke University
  Rand reprints;RAND/RP-347
  Labor policy -- Russia (Federation)
- Immigration and labor markets: some thoughts about the western experience and implications for the Russian case (Reports 013967), 1995 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Emigration and immigration -- Russia (Federation); Labor supply -- Russia (Federation)
- Potential energy: emergent emigration of highly qualified manpower from the former Soviet Union (Reports 013968), 1994 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Dissertation;RGSD-113;Dissertation (Rand Graduate School);RGSD-113.
  Professional employees -- Former Soviet republics; Brain drain -- Former Soviet republics; Scientists -- Former Soviet republics
- High security towns: a job force migration Russian (Reports 013969), 1995 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Discusses the demographic situation in military and semi-military establishments in terms of job market, income levels, etc., conditions which will eventually drive out the work force.
- The resettlement of refugees and forced migrants in the Russian Federation Russian (Reports 013970), 1994 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  In Russian.
  Refugees -- Russia (Federation)
- Population migration and the labor market in Russia (Reports 013971), 1995 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Title sufficient for abstract. Copies in English and Russian.
  Migration, Internal -- Russia (Federation); Migration, Internal -- Former Soviet republics; Labor market -- Former Soviet republics; Labor market -- Russia (Federation)
- Migrants in the Moscow job market, Russian (Reports 013972), 1995 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Labor supply -- Russia (Federation) -- Moscow (Russia); Migrant labor -- Russia (Federation) -- Moscow (Russia)
- Training visit: Valentin Tikhonov, Senior Researcher, Laboratory for Migration Studies, Center for Demography and Human Ecology (Reports 013973), 1995 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  RAND conducted a month-long training seminar for research and programming skils in June, 1995 for Valentin Tikhonov, senior researcher at the Institute for Migration Studies at the Center for Demography and Human Ecology in Moscow.
- World-wide conventional arms trade (1994-2000): a forecast and analysis, December 1994. (Reports 013974) (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  The Office of the Under Secretary of Defense (Acquisition and Technology) conducted this study to provide an analytical basis for conventional arms transfers decisions--Pref.
  09500258
  British American Security Information Council
  World wide conventional arms trade (1994-2000)
  Arms transfers; Military weapons; Military assistance, American
- Proceedings of the 6th International Conference on Thai Studies, Chiang Mai, Thailand, 14-17 (Reports 013975), 1996 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Asia/Southeast Asia
  09651190
  Chiang Mai University
  Related Grant Purpose
  Support for women and gender relations panels at Sixth International Conference on Thai Studies.
  Kanprachum Nana Chat Thaisuksa: Thai Studies 6th International Conference, Chiang Mai, 1996
  International Conference on Thai Studies (6th: 1996: Chiang Mai, Thailand)
  Area studies -- Congresses; Foreign study -- Congresses
- Transmitting race: the Los Angeles riot in television news (Reports 013976), 1994 (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Governance and Public Policy
  09301201
  President and Fellows of Harvard College
  Research paper (Joan Shorenstein Barone Center on the Press, Politics, and Public Policy;R-11
  Mass media and race relations; Riots -- California -- Los Angeles (Calif.); African Americans -- California -- Los Angeles (Calif.)
- The economic war among the states, June 1996. (Reports 013977) (Box 743, Reel R-9299)
  Reports on the proceedings of "The Economic War Among the States", a conference held in Washington, D.C., in May of 1996.
  Governance and Public Policy;Media
  09600321
  Minnesota Public Radio
  Region (Minneapolis, Minn.)
  Industrial policy -- United States -- States; Economic development projects -- United States -- States; Industrial promotion -- United States -- States
- The economic war among the states: National Conference, May 21-22, 1996, National Academy of Sciences (Reports 013978) (Box 744, Reel R-9299)
  Industrial policy -- United States -- States; Economic development projects -- United States -- States; Industrial promotion -- United States -- States; Economic development projects -- Southern States
- A review of the ACE Fellows Program, 1993. (Reports 013979) (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  09000952
  American Council on Education (ACE)
  College administrators -- In-service training -- United States
- ACE Fellows Program: summary of the program review, 1993. (Reports 013980) (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
- Chemical dependency treatment alternative study: report on the findings from the study's focus group meetings (Reports 013981), 1994 (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  09301512
  State of Minnesota
  Substance abuse -- Treatment -- Minnesota; Drug abuse -- Minnesota
- Florida Marine Spill Analysis System (Reports 013982), 1996 (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Description of a program which received an Innovations in State and Local Government Award.
  09401317
  State of Florida
  Marine pollution -- Florida; Chemical spills -- Florida; Oil spills -- Florida; Environmental policy -- Florida
- FORTROP'96: International Conference on Tropical Forestry in the 21st Century, Kesetsart University, Bangkok, Thailand, 25-29 November 1996. (Reports 013983) (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Program and informational booklet for the conference.
  Vietnam
  09750144
  Kasetsart University
  International Conference on Forestry in the 21st Century (1996: Kasetsart University)
  Rain forests -- Congresses; Sustainable forestry -- Tropics -- Congresses; Forest conservation -- Congresses
- Bio-intensive agriculture training programme: July - September quarterly report, Oct. (Reports 013985), 1997 (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  09550429
  Manor House Agricultural Centre
  Agriculture -- Africa
- Vote for me: politics in America: a four-part series for public television 1995 /produced by Paul Stekler, Louis Alvarez and Andrew Kolker. (Reports 013990) (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Plans for producing the series for public television.
  Governance and Public Policy;United States and International Affairs Program/Office of the Vice President
  09401425
  The Greater Washington Educational Telecommunications Association, Inc.
  Elections -- United States
- Strategies to secure rural entitlement: National Workshop of Grass Root Action Groups, 18-19-20 July 1986, New Delhi, 1986. (Reports 013991) (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Conference proceedings. Title sufficient as abstract.
  Asia/India, Nepal and Sri Lanka
  08300692
  Banwasi Seva Ashram
  National Workshop of Grass Root Action Groups (1986: New Delhi, India)
  Political participation -- India -- Congresses; Rural development -- India -- Congresses
- ICDDR,B: Donors' Meeting, Nov. 20-21 (Reports 013992), 1988 (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  "Document has been prepared specifically for a meeting in November 1988 of the international donors who generously support ICDDR,B. It is intended to provide them with substance for their discussions" (Preface, page i).[…]Document prepared for a meeting of donors to the International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh.
  Developing Countries Program
  08800888
  International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh
  ICDDR-B Donors' Meeting (1988: Dhaka, Bangladesh)
  Diarrhea -- Congresses -- Bangladesh; Medical care -- Congresses -- Bangladesh; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Congresses
- A three day retreat program of the Institute for Effective Partnerships: East Coast Regional Retreat, November 8, 9, and 10, 1996, Mohonk Mountain House, New Paltz, New York: retreat focus: Revitalizing your partnership for future challenges: a reflecti (Reports 013993) (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  A sponsored event by the National Center for Urban Partnerships and the American Council on Education. Retreat workbook for urban educators.
  08900573
  Revitalizing your partnership for future challenges: a reflective and self-assessment workshop program to facilitate greater team effectiveness
  Education, Urban -- United States; Teachers -- United States
- Family, marriage and children: selected international human rights instruments, April 1986. (Reports 013994) (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Compilation of major substantive provisions drawn from those international human rights instruments and standard-setting documents that pertain to human rights within the family and within marriage and the human rights of children.
  Rights and Social Justice;International Affairs;Developing Countries Program
  08400115
  The International Centre for the Legal Protection of Human Rights
  Human rights; Family -- Civil rights; Child welfare (International law)
- Who is delivering the goods in a changing economy?: an opportunity to redefine the social contract: a report of the roundtable proceedings (Reports 013995), 1994 (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Proceedings of roundtable conducted as part of the Nonprofit Government Contracting Project. Roundtable held at the Xerox Document University & Training Center, Leesburg, Virginia, March 1994.
  09300224
  Union Institute
  Public contracts -- United States; Non-profit organizations -- United States
- State professional standards/practices commissions or boards: a policy analysis paper (Reports 013996), 1988 (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Discusses teacher certification and standards and the role of professionals in education.
  Urban Poverty program; Education and Culture
  08600894
  American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education
  Teachers -- Certification -- United States; Teachers -- Training of -- United States -- Standards
- Educators as lawmakers: a directory of state legislators from the education profession, 1986. (Reports 013997) (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Legislators -- United States -- States -- Directories
- State policies and institutional responses to demands for alternative licensure (Reports 013998), 1996 (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Discusses alternative teacher licensure procedures as a way of coping with teacher shortages.
  Teachers -- Certification -- United States
- State policies to promote P-16 collaboration: a survey of professional development and P-12 content standards (Reports 013999), 1996 (Box 744, Reel R-9300)
  Discusses state government roles in preservice teacher training and professional development.
  Teachers -- Certification -- United States; Teachers -- Training of -- United States
- The American News Service: an evaluation of the pilot project, May 1-December 31, 1995, January 1996. (Reports 014000) (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  Evaluation of a project by the Center for Living Democracy to improve the way Americans view the nation's social problems.
  09651372
  Institute for the Arts of Democracy
  Mass media -- United States; Press -- United States
- A National Gathering: college educators and service learning, Providence, Rhode Island, May 11-14, 1995. (Reports 014001) (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  Schedule and agenda for the conference.
  09000453
  Education Commission of the States
  National Gathering: College Educators and Service Learning (1995: Providence, R.I.)
  Student service -- United States -- Congresses; College and community -- United States -- Congresses
- Colorado Campus Compact: 1994 Institute on Integrating Service with Academic Study, Fort Lewis College: action plans, June 1994. (Reports 014002) (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  Conference to develop Action Plans for integrating service into college curricula.
  Institute on Integrating Service with Academic Study (1994: Fort Lewis College)
- Gender and management in the South African public service (Reports 014003), 1995 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  The objectives of the study ... are to: provide a baseline data and the nature of gender representation in public service management. Assess the situation and position of women in public service. Examine the past and present legislative policy responses.
  Africa and the Middle East/South Africa
  09301213
  University of the Witwatersrand
  Support for research on gender and structural reform in the South African civil service.
  Public service employment -- South Africa; Civil service -- South Africa; Minorities -- Employment -- South Africa; Discrimination in employment -- South Africa; Sex discrimination -- South Africa
- The new mercantilism: where is business leading our foreign policy? (Reports 014005-001), 1996 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  Title sufficient as abstract. Delivered at the Wilson Center's "End of the American Century?" conference.
  Rights and Social Justice;International Affairs;Governance and Public Policy;Peace and Social Justice/Governance and Civil Society; Urban Poverty program
  08900449
  The Woodrow Wilson National Fellowship Foundation
  Working paper (Woodrow Wilson Center for International Scholars. International Studies Program)
  International relations
- A new protectionism?: tariffs versus free trade (Reports 014005-002), 1996 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  International trade; Tariff
- A new international economic order? (Reports 014006), 1996 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  Title sufficient as abstract. Delivered at the Wilson Center's End of the American Century conference.
  International economic relations; World politics
- Yugoslavia, 1991-92: could diplomacy have prevented a tragedy? (Reports 014007), 1993 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  Support for a program to prepare and encourage minority students to enter careers in domestic and international public servie.
  Pew case studies in international affairs;453
  Political science -- Yugoslavia
- Trade protection and industrial revitalization: American steel in the 1980s (Reports 014008), 1993 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  Governance and Public Policy;Rights and Social Justice
  09001344
  Economic Policy Institute
  Working paper (Economic Policy Institute);no. 104
  Steel industry and trade -- United States; Steel industry and trade -- Government policy -- United States; Protectionism -- United States
- Good jobs at good wages: The characteristics of jobs created by lifting line-of-business restrictions in telecommunications for Baby Bells (Reports 014009), 1993 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  Working paper (Economic Policy Institute);no. 108
  Telecommunication -- United States -- Deregulation; Job creation -- United States -- Statistics; Telecommunication policy -- United States; Labor market -- United States -- Statistics
- A review of the Ford Foundation's impact on higher education in Africa (Reports 014013-001), 2000 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  As part of ongoing program development and evaluation, this study was undertaken "to understand the impact of Foundation support for educational reform and policy initiatives, as well as higher education's contribution to development initiatives. This stu
  Education, Higher -- Africa
- A review of the Ford Foundation's impact on higher education in Africa, March 2000, Appendix I (Reports 014013-002)
- A review of the Ford Foundation's impact on higher education in Africa, March 2000, Appendix II (Reports 014013-003)
- The reminiscences of Sanford Jaffe (Reports 014014), 2000 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)
  Interviews conducted as research for a dissertation on the history of public interest law.
  Public interest law -- History
- Preliminary inventory, Accession 5230: Douglas Ensminger (1910-1989), papers (Reports 014015), 1999 (Box 745, Reel R-9300)